<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>epidemiology | Phylodynamics</title>
    <link>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/tags/epidemiology/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://InfrPopGen.github.io/tags/epidemiology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>epidemiology</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© S.W. Attwood, 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 20:28:30 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/img/ez01.jpg</url>
      <title>epidemiology</title>
      <link>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/tags/epidemiology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is SARS-CoV-2 evolving?</title>
      <link>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/blog/sars2_evolving/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 20:28:30 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/blog/sars2_evolving/</guid>
      <description>












&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://InfrPopGen.github.io/img/ARTIClogo.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://InfrPopGen.github.io/img/ARTIClogo.png&#34; alt=&#34;ARTIC logo&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;200&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An April 28th paper featuring a SARS-CoV-2 phylogenetic tree provoked the ire of many evolutionary virologists&lt;/strong&gt;―the paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/content/117/17/9241&#34;&gt;(Forster et al. 2020)&lt;/a&gt; appeared in &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences USA (PNAS)&lt;/em&gt; which is a prestigious journal, so what could have upset the evolutionary biology community so much? Alarm bells probably began to ring at this point in the abstract &amp;lsquo;The network faithfully traces routes of infections for documented coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) cases, indicating that phylogenetic networks can likewise be successfully used to help trace undocumented COVID-19 infection sources&amp;rsquo;. First problem is that SARS-CoV-2 transmits itself on average once a week, but it accumulates variants around once a fortnight, so there is not the resolution to unravel a series of transmissions close together in time. A bigger problem is sampling―the authors infer a chain of transmission from China to Germany to Italy to Mexico, but this is not at all certain. If a &amp;ldquo;German&amp;rdquo; variant was quite common in China (or Italy) but was not often sampled because, for example, sampling was biased to cases in a particular city hospital and by chance this variant was common in a rural area, then it can appear that a variant arose in Germany and passed to Italy, when in fact it came from a third country. Last but not least, the authors observed certain variants in certain parts of the world that defined lineages on their tree (East Asian, European, and US/Australian) and they proposed that this divergence was due to selection for variants that favoured the virus in each particular part of the world. In fact there was no reason to imagine selection and adaptation because &lt;strong&gt;founder effects&lt;/strong&gt; can explain their tree, without any selection. As people caught flights around the world, some variants went with them and some did not, and some were transmitted onward in the other countries and some were not. The result was founding populations in each region that differed, each with its own spectrum of variants and their frequencies, but all shaped by chance. As the outbreaks grew into a pandemic, these differences were amplified, because a common variant is more likely to be involved in a transmission event (so making it more common), to produce the differences that Forster et al. attributed to selection. A variant a low frequency is more likely to be lost by chance, for example only a few self-isolating cases need to be effective. We call this accidental loss &lt;strong&gt;genetic drift&lt;/strong&gt; because the variant frequencies drift by chance (selection isn&#39;t pushing them). Some variants are lost by chance, and some might reach quite high percentages in the populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/nsr/nwaa036&#34;&gt;Tang et al. 2020&lt;/a&gt; attracted similar criticism when they inferred selection for the virus during its first entry into the human population. The first problem was, again that one lineage had been inferred to be spreading faster and coming to dominate the population. The authors defined two &amp;ldquo;strains&amp;rdquo; (we prefer to call them lineages, until a very convincing case has been made for real biological differences among them) on the basis of posession of two variants (one of which was non-synonymous, i.e. it changed the amino acid coded for). The S (for serine) lineage lacked the variants (relative to the ancestral genome, which should be oldest SARS-CoV-2 genome we can find or infer, but this is a separate problem, see below) and the L (for leucine) lineage had them. Consequently, Tang et al. regarded the &amp;ldquo;S-strain&amp;rdquo; as ancestral, and L as derived from it. As L was derived, but more common (then ~70% of isolates sequenced) than S, the authors assumed that L had arisen and outcompeted S. The assumption that S is &amp;ldquo;evolutionarily older and less aggressive&amp;rdquo; can be questioned, as we did above with regard to founder effects. A second problem here is that of sampling bias, because only detected cases get sequenced, and detected cases are often related to one another (i.e. not independent samples). For example, a particular hospital might have good links with a sequencing consortium and so many genomes are sequenced from its locality, our database are also biased towards cases in cities. On top of this, the scope and depth of sampling varies by country―by early March most of the cases were in China, but 60% of the genomic data were coming from cases elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second problem is a little more subtle. The authors aimed to detect selection using the number of non-synonymous (dN) to synonymous (dS) &lt;strong&gt;substitutions&lt;/strong&gt; (substitutions are mutations that stick in a population through the time we sample). If part of the genome (called a &lt;strong&gt;locus&lt;/strong&gt;) has a low dN/dS it could be that purifying selection is removing genomes with altered amino acid sequences, so as to keep the locus unchanged, except for synonymous changes that only affect the RNA sequence, not the protein. We might then regard such conserved loci as important to success of the virus in some way. The first problem with this relates to sequencing errors; these are rare, because unlike real mutations they can&#39;t be transmitted, and have a higher non-synonymous to synonymous ratio because, again unlike real mutations, they have equal chance of occurring at a first codon as at a third codon. Consequently, such errors can cause an apparent excess of low-frequency non-synonymous substitutions which will mimic purifying selection. Second, because in a population there are always more non-synonymous substitutions than synonymous ones, and because most mutations are rare, there is more chance of sampling a synonymous substitution many times; this makes non-synonymous mutations look rarer than they really are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there was a view that Tang et al. had a problem with their rooting. The root of a phylogenetic tree (or a cluster of branches on a tree, which can be called a &lt;strong&gt;clade&lt;/strong&gt;) is where you decide to put the origin of all the organisms, phylogenetics calls the things on a tree &lt;strong&gt;taxa&lt;/strong&gt; (singular taxon), so the root is the ancestor of all the taxa on the tree. The &lt;strong&gt;derived&lt;/strong&gt; taxa on the authors&amp;rsquo; tree should be those with a substitution relative to the sequence for the last common ancestor of the epidemic in China; however, it looked like they had used the &lt;strong&gt;Most Recent Common Ancestor&lt;/strong&gt; (MRCA) not of the epidemic, but of the virus (SARS-CoV-2) and its closest known relative, the bat-CoV (&lt;strong&gt;bat coronavirus&lt;/strong&gt;) RaTG13. The evolutionary distance back to this MRCA (the one with the bat-CoV) is much greater than that to the MRCA of the epidemic, because the time scales are decades, not months. The bigger distance allows back mutations (back to the ancestral state) to occur, so we won&#39;t be able to tell which substitutions are derived and which are not. The problem of back mutation will affect new synonymous mutations more than new non-synonymous ones because synonymous sites have higher substitution rates. The back mutation is back to the real common ancestor of the epidemic, and can be removal of slightly harmful mutations by positive selection, but it looks like a derived mutation away from the MRCA with the bat-CoV. So we can see the effect of not using the MRCA of the epidemic as the root, in a study where we are looking for selection in the epidemic (not the wrong root, but the wrong root for this particular analysis)―the effect is that the faux &amp;ldquo;derived&amp;rdquo; substitutions make it look like we have an excess of high-frequency synonymous substitutions when we don&#39;t, and to a potentially false conclusion of purifying selection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors also identified &amp;ldquo;derived&amp;rdquo; variants that they presented as favouring transmission or virulence, but this was not convincing to many researchers. You can read more about these problems in &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/ve/veaa034&#34;&gt;MacLean et al 2020&lt;/a&gt; and for a general warning of the pitfalls relating to inferring selection and new virulent strains of SARS-CoV-2, this is a good read &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41564-020-0738-5&#34;&gt;Villabona-Arenas, Hanage &amp;amp; Tully, 2020&lt;/a&gt;. I think the general rule is, try not to get lost in your own analysis. Imagine you are someone else, a critical reviewer, and ask, what else could explain what I am seeing, aside from what I want to be true?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Publish what you see, not what you think is there!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top image: &amp;ldquo;The logo of the ARTIC network&amp;rdquo; Credit: &lt;a href=&#34;https://artic.network/&#34;&gt;ARTIC Network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A virus goes missing―genomics explains reappearance of lost virus</title>
      <link>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/blog/frozenevol/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 10:48:46 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/blog/frozenevol/</guid>
      <description>












&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://InfrPopGen.github.io/img/BTVphylo.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://InfrPopGen.github.io/img/BTVphylo.png&#34; alt=&#34;phylogeny for BTV8&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;400&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This investigation into the re-emergence of Bluetongue virus serotype 8 (BTV-8)&lt;/strong&gt; in France 2015 is a fine example of phylogenetic epidemiology in action. In the 2006 outbreak BTV spread to affect 16 countries and killed many livestock animals, particularly sheep, with losses to European agriculture in the billions of Euros. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluetongue_disease&#34;&gt;BTV is an arthropod-borne virus&lt;/a&gt; of ruminants and was considered successfully controlled through vaccination by early 2010, but is now enzootic to France. Consequently, David Pascall, Kyriaki Nomikou, and colleagues in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gla.ac.uk/researchinstitutes/iii/cvr/staff/groups/palmarinigroup/&#34;&gt;Glasgow&lt;/a&gt; and across Europe, sought to explain the unexpected outbreak in France by applying phylogenetics to a data-set of 164 complete BTV-8 genomes sampled throughout the first (2006-2009) and second (2015) outbreaks. Cessation of vaccination in 2010 was followed by a steady decline in seropositivity in cattle until 2014; thus a reintroduction (rather than cryptic sub-clinical transmission) appeared likely. To avoid culture effects most samples were taken directly from infected cattle. The phylogeny showed genomes of the second outbreak to be monophyletic (all in one clade or lineage, with no other genomes mixed in) and entirely nested within those of the first. Notably, the branch linking the two outbreaks was suspiciously short given the substitution rate of BTV-8 and the five years between the outbreaks. The ancestral sequence was reconstructed for the second outbreak and found to differ at only 4 sites from its closest relative in the first epidemic, whereas samples collected in 2006 differed from those in 2008 by up to 56 sites. Indeed root-to-tip regression (of tree branch lengths against sampling times), applied to a tree that included the reconstructed ancestor of the second outbreak, dated the ancestor as having been circulating in late March 2008. The authors were able to effectively rule out dormancy in some life-stage of the arthropod vector, and latency in some accessory host, because five years was just too long. Noting that BTV has been detected in the semen of viraemic bulls and rams, the authors proposed that the 2015 outbreak may have arisen from use of frozen semen, embryos or colostrum, which is a common practice in livestock farming. The study has been published in PLoS Biology and is available open-access directly from the publisher &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3000673&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top image: &amp;ldquo;Timescaled phylogenetic tree of BTV-8 samples collected during the European outbreaks between 2006 and 2018&amp;rdquo; by Pascall DJ, Nomikou K, Bréard E, Zientara S, Filipe AdS, Hoffmann B, et al. &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3000673&#34;&gt;2020&lt;/a&gt;, used under &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Population Growth Trend Analysis for Neotricula aperta, the Snail Intermediate Host of Schistosoma mekongi, after Construction of the Pak-Mun Dam</title>
      <link>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/publication/attwood-population-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/publication/attwood-population-2013/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schistosomiasis in the Mekong region: epidemiology and phylogeography</title>
      <link>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/publication/attwood-schistosomiasis-2001/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/publication/attwood-schistosomiasis-2001/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
