<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>virology | Phylodynamics</title>
    <link>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/tags/virology/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://InfrPopGen.github.io/tags/virology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>virology</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© S.W. Attwood, 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 15:15:04 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/img/ez01.jpg</url>
      <title>virology</title>
      <link>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/tags/virology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of the human–virus interaction in COVID-19</title>
      <link>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/blog/sars_evol_immunity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 15:15:04 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/blog/sars_evol_immunity/</guid>
      <description>












&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://InfrPopGen.github.io/img/clonotypes.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://InfrPopGen.github.io/img/clonotypes.png&#34; alt=&#34;heatmap&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt; If there is unfamiliar terminology here, then it may help to read these posts in order, starting with &amp;ldquo;Is SARS-CoV-2 evolving?&amp;rdquo; of 18th May 2020. Definitions of terms are in bold to help in finding them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phylogenetics can give clues about how SARS-CoV-2 battles the anti-viral responses of its hosts&lt;/strong&gt;―two recent papers considered the C-&amp;gt;U hypermutation which, like other coronaviruses, is a feature of the SARS-CoV-2 genome. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.05.01.072330&#34;&gt;Peter Simmonds&amp;rsquo; preprint&lt;/a&gt; focused on treating the low &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CpG_site&#34;&gt;CpG content&lt;/a&gt; of the CoV genomes as a phylogenetic character that tells us something about events in their history, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.abb5813&#34;&gt;the paper by Salvatore Giorgio et al (2020)&lt;/a&gt; gives further examination of the anti-viral aspects. Simmonds noted that there are about four times the number of C-&amp;gt;U transitions in the SARS-CoV-2 genome than expected by chance, which is high even among RNA viruses, and that around half of non-synonymous mutations are C-&amp;gt;U substitutions―suggesting they might be important in the evolution of the virus (but see below). This excess increases 10-fold if the C-&amp;gt;U is flanked by a certain &lt;strong&gt;motif&lt;/strong&gt; (i.e. specific sequence pattern), which Simmonds noted are favoured by certain &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4930407/&#34;&gt;APOBEC&lt;/a&gt; proteins. Some APOBECs are thought able to introduce mutations to RNA viral genomes by deamination of cytidines, with the mutations introduced as an anti-viral defence. The fact that these viruses show low GC content, but the G+A content is relatively normal, would fit with an APOBEC acting on the genomic (positive) strand of the virus, exposed in the cytoplasm, before replication complex formation―otherwise both strands would be present, and susceptible to mutation as the genome is replicated―the GA content would then fall with the GC. The same idea (lack of symmetry) argues against the mutations being errors of the &lt;strong&gt;viral RdRp&lt;/strong&gt; (RNA-dependent RNA-polymerase, the enzyme that the viruses uses to copy its own genome). APOBEC RNA-editing would also explain the strangely high dN/dS ratio in SARS-CoV-2 because it would not be shaped by natural selection. Indeed, we would have APOBEC introducing variants and natural selection removing any that were deleterious. Of course, we can imagine that these viruses would evolve to avoid using sequences that APOBECs target; however, there is a diverse family of APOBECs and they vary among host species. Simmonds observed that the hypermutation is greatest in close relatives of SARS-CoV-2 and reduces as more divergent lineages are considered; this could be because the human SARS-CoVs have only recently begun to infect humans, whereas the seasonal CoVs that have long circulated in humans have adapted to our APOBECs and restored their GC content. The implication is that SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 are still adapted to bat APOBECs (or to whatever the ancestral hosts were). Giorgio et al. take the story a little further, and look at another deanimase family, the ADARs, as well as APOBEC; they found frequently overrepresented stop codons in transcribed viral RNAs rather than genomic, which supported an anti-viral role for these enzymes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we tend to learn most from papers that attract criticism, I should mention the &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msaa094&#34;&gt;paper in MBE by Xia (2020)&lt;/a&gt; here. Xia came up with a nice idea (those are often the ones that are most questioned), as he found CpG levels in some canine alphacoronaviruses as low as in SARS-CoV-2, the record holder for low CpG among these CoVs (although human seasonal cold virus CoV HKU1 might be lower). He reasoned that the ancestor of SARS-CoV-2 may have been subjected to a canine immune environment, and on that basis argued that SARS-CoV-2 jumped from bats to some canine and then to humans. In a recent (aren&#39;t they all?) preprint &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.05.08.083816v1&#34;&gt;Digard et al (2020)&lt;/a&gt; aligned nearly 200 genomes of SARS-CoVs and various coronaviruses transmitting in animals. They found that although CpG levels were lowest in human and canine coronaviruses and highest in bat and rodent, there was much range overlap, which makes Xia&#39;s nice idea more shaky. These authors all noted that the low CpG may well be to avoid the action of Zinc-finger Antiviral Protein (ZAP), which binds to viral RNAs at their CpG motifs (an addition to the APOBEC explanation). Interestingly, Digard&#39;s group found almost normal CpG levels at two loci, &lt;em&gt;E ORF&lt;/em&gt; and the coding region of &lt;em&gt;ORF10&lt;/em&gt; (an ORF is an &lt;strong&gt;Open Reading Frame&lt;/strong&gt;, the coding part of a gene that can be translated, but viruses can have overlapping ORFs, or &amp;ldquo;sub-ORFs&amp;rdquo; if you like, that&#39;s not an official term!). These two loci also showed much less CpG suppression than the rest of their genomes in bat- and pangolin-CoVs sampled nearly a decade ago. The implication is that selection had not removed this pattern over the years, and so it is a derived trait that was selected for before SARS-CoVs began to transmit widely among humans. In support of this, a phylogenetic tree estimated with only &lt;em&gt;E ORF&lt;/em&gt; sequences for the 7 human-CoVs and 96 bat-CoVs showed the human-CoVs scattered among the bat-CoV lineages and with CpG levels matching their closest bat-CoV relatives. They suggest that the high CpG in &lt;em&gt;E ORF&lt;/em&gt; might be because it is transcribed late in the infection process, when attack by ZAP is less of a problem. By the way, Xia is also the author of &lt;a href=&#34;http://dambe.bio.uottawa.ca/DAMBE/dambe.aspx&#34;&gt;DAMBE&lt;/a&gt; which I used in most of my 1990s papers! It&#39;s worth checking out, if you don&#39;t know it―not now the best for phylogenetics but its other features are handy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;E ORF&lt;/em&gt; story is a good example of how phylogenetics can help us understand the anti-viral reponses during infection, and the strategies SARS-CoV-2 has been using to avoid them as it evolved and moved from host to host. Now let&#39;s look at some sequencing studies on the immune response itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;APOBECS are part of the interferon-induced innate immune response (they have links with adaptive response too, but that is another topic), but &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.05.20.106294v1&#34;&gt;Galson et al (2020)&lt;/a&gt; use sequencing data, and a nearest-neighbour kind of clustering algorithm, to directly explore the humoral immune response to SARS-CoV-2. They compared the IGHA and IGHG B-Cell Receptor (BCR) sequences for 19 patients with those for healthy individuals. The numbers of mutations showed a bimodal frequency plot (i.e. two humps), which suggests an expanding population―i.e. a population of B-cells that had only just &amp;ldquo;switched&amp;rdquo; on to the presence of the virus. Nevertheless, the larger clonal expansions revealed by the sequence network showed many mutations, which fits with their having activated from memory of a previously encountered antigen. Convergent BCR sequences were also seen, with very similar sequences among different patients, and even between UK and US studies; this convergence is good news for vaccine development, as it implies that a vaccine that works across diverse lineages of virus is feasible. We also saw signs of activation from memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To counter that possibly good news, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.05.21.109272v1&#34;&gt;Cheng et al. (2020)&amp;lsquo;s preprint&lt;/a&gt; is potentially worrying, but models are never perfect so&amp;hellip;. These authors modelled the shape (and charge) of the &amp;ldquo;spike&amp;rdquo; protein, which is what the virus uses to recognise ACE2 receptors on our cells and trigger the process of cell entry. The models indicated a 20 amino acid motif in spike that mimics a superantigen called staphylococcal entero-toxin B (SEB), which is known to be the trigger for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.qedbio.com/blog/superantigens-elicit-cytokine-storm-responsible-t-cells-identified/&#34;&gt;toxic shock or the cytokine storm&lt;/a&gt; in humans. In SARS-CoV-2 the motif appears to be palindromic so, when the reverse direction is also included, this doubles the stretch of sequence to match with the superantigen peptide. The superantigen motif is not found in any other SARS coronavirus, such as SARS-CoV from the 2002-2004 outbreak. Probably most controversially the models indicate that some &lt;strong&gt;Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms&lt;/strong&gt; (SNPs, or substitutions at a single site that persist in a population at non-negligible frequencies) currently circulating in Europe and the US may increase the superantigenicity of the SEB-like motif. Among these is the infamous D641G, which I have to write about next, which may interact with MHCII to strengthen the association with T-cell receptors involved in cytokine storm initiation. The authors suggest that this may explain the higher rates of cytokine storm in Europe and US and the appearance in Europe of SARS-CoV-2 related inflammatory syndrome in children. It is important to note that without a heap of empirical evidence to back these suggestions, the indications of computer models are just that, indications only. After all, there are many possible explanations for many things!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS Just for fun, you may want to think about what the implications are of C-&amp;gt;G hypermutation, especially by APOBECs, on phylogenetics (i.e. on estimating evolutionary trees). How might that affect our SARS-CoV-2 evolutionary trees?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top image: &amp;ldquo;Heatmap of the 777 convergent COVID-19-associated clonotypes (observed between 4 or more COVID-19 participants)&amp;rdquo; by Galson, J. D.; Schaetzle, S.; Bashford-Rogers, R. J. M.; Raybould, M. I. J.; Kovaltsuk, A.; Kilpatrick, G. J.; Minter, R.; Finch, D. K.; Dias, J.; James, L.; Thomas, G., et al. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.05.20.106294v1&#34;&gt;2020&lt;/a&gt;, used under &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is SARS-CoV-2 evolving?</title>
      <link>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/blog/sars2_evolving/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 20:28:30 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/blog/sars2_evolving/</guid>
      <description>












&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://InfrPopGen.github.io/img/ARTIClogo.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://InfrPopGen.github.io/img/ARTIClogo.png&#34; alt=&#34;ARTIC logo&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;200&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An April 28th paper featuring a SARS-CoV-2 phylogenetic tree provoked the ire of many evolutionary virologists&lt;/strong&gt;―the paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/content/117/17/9241&#34;&gt;(Forster et al. 2020)&lt;/a&gt; appeared in &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences USA (PNAS)&lt;/em&gt; which is a prestigious journal, so what could have upset the evolutionary biology community so much? Alarm bells probably began to ring at this point in the abstract &amp;lsquo;The network faithfully traces routes of infections for documented coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) cases, indicating that phylogenetic networks can likewise be successfully used to help trace undocumented COVID-19 infection sources&amp;rsquo;. First problem is that SARS-CoV-2 transmits itself on average once a week, but it accumulates variants around once a fortnight, so there is not the resolution to unravel a series of transmissions close together in time. A bigger problem is sampling―the authors infer a chain of transmission from China to Germany to Italy to Mexico, but this is not at all certain. If a &amp;ldquo;German&amp;rdquo; variant was quite common in China (or Italy) but was not often sampled because, for example, sampling was biased to cases in a particular city hospital and by chance this variant was common in a rural area, then it can appear that a variant arose in Germany and passed to Italy, when in fact it came from a third country. Last but not least, the authors observed certain variants in certain parts of the world that defined lineages on their tree (East Asian, European, and US/Australian) and they proposed that this divergence was due to selection for variants that favoured the virus in each particular part of the world. In fact there was no reason to imagine selection and adaptation because &lt;strong&gt;founder effects&lt;/strong&gt; can explain their tree, without any selection. As people caught flights around the world, some variants went with them and some did not, and some were transmitted onward in the other countries and some were not. The result was founding populations in each region that differed, each with its own spectrum of variants and their frequencies, but all shaped by chance. As the outbreaks grew into a pandemic, these differences were amplified, because a common variant is more likely to be involved in a transmission event (so making it more common), to produce the differences that Forster et al. attributed to selection. A variant a low frequency is more likely to be lost by chance, for example only a few self-isolating cases need to be effective. We call this accidental loss &lt;strong&gt;genetic drift&lt;/strong&gt; because the variant frequencies drift by chance (selection isn&#39;t pushing them). Some variants are lost by chance, and some might reach quite high percentages in the populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/nsr/nwaa036&#34;&gt;Tang et al. 2020&lt;/a&gt; attracted similar criticism when they inferred selection for the virus during its first entry into the human population. The first problem was, again that one lineage had been inferred to be spreading faster and coming to dominate the population. The authors defined two &amp;ldquo;strains&amp;rdquo; (we prefer to call them lineages, until a very convincing case has been made for real biological differences among them) on the basis of posession of two variants (one of which was non-synonymous, i.e. it changed the amino acid coded for). The S (for serine) lineage lacked the variants (relative to the ancestral genome, which should be oldest SARS-CoV-2 genome we can find or infer, but this is a separate problem, see below) and the L (for leucine) lineage had them. Consequently, Tang et al. regarded the &amp;ldquo;S-strain&amp;rdquo; as ancestral, and L as derived from it. As L was derived, but more common (then ~70% of isolates sequenced) than S, the authors assumed that L had arisen and outcompeted S. The assumption that S is &amp;ldquo;evolutionarily older and less aggressive&amp;rdquo; can be questioned, as we did above with regard to founder effects. A second problem here is that of sampling bias, because only detected cases get sequenced, and detected cases are often related to one another (i.e. not independent samples). For example, a particular hospital might have good links with a sequencing consortium and so many genomes are sequenced from its locality, our database are also biased towards cases in cities. On top of this, the scope and depth of sampling varies by country―by early March most of the cases were in China, but 60% of the genomic data were coming from cases elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second problem is a little more subtle. The authors aimed to detect selection using the number of non-synonymous (dN) to synonymous (dS) &lt;strong&gt;substitutions&lt;/strong&gt; (substitutions are mutations that stick in a population through the time we sample). If part of the genome (called a &lt;strong&gt;locus&lt;/strong&gt;) has a low dN/dS it could be that purifying selection is removing genomes with altered amino acid sequences, so as to keep the locus unchanged, except for synonymous changes that only affect the RNA sequence, not the protein. We might then regard such conserved loci as important to success of the virus in some way. The first problem with this relates to sequencing errors; these are rare, because unlike real mutations they can&#39;t be transmitted, and have a higher non-synonymous to synonymous ratio because, again unlike real mutations, they have equal chance of occurring at a first codon as at a third codon. Consequently, such errors can cause an apparent excess of low-frequency non-synonymous substitutions which will mimic purifying selection. Second, because in a population there are always more non-synonymous substitutions than synonymous ones, and because most mutations are rare, there is more chance of sampling a synonymous substitution many times; this makes non-synonymous mutations look rarer than they really are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there was a view that Tang et al. had a problem with their rooting. The root of a phylogenetic tree (or a cluster of branches on a tree, which can be called a &lt;strong&gt;clade&lt;/strong&gt;) is where you decide to put the origin of all the organisms, phylogenetics calls the things on a tree &lt;strong&gt;taxa&lt;/strong&gt; (singular taxon), so the root is the ancestor of all the taxa on the tree. The &lt;strong&gt;derived&lt;/strong&gt; taxa on the authors&amp;rsquo; tree should be those with a substitution relative to the sequence for the last common ancestor of the epidemic in China; however, it looked like they had used the &lt;strong&gt;Most Recent Common Ancestor&lt;/strong&gt; (MRCA) not of the epidemic, but of the virus (SARS-CoV-2) and its closest known relative, the bat-CoV (&lt;strong&gt;bat coronavirus&lt;/strong&gt;) RaTG13. The evolutionary distance back to this MRCA (the one with the bat-CoV) is much greater than that to the MRCA of the epidemic, because the time scales are decades, not months. The bigger distance allows back mutations (back to the ancestral state) to occur, so we won&#39;t be able to tell which substitutions are derived and which are not. The problem of back mutation will affect new synonymous mutations more than new non-synonymous ones because synonymous sites have higher substitution rates. The back mutation is back to the real common ancestor of the epidemic, and can be removal of slightly harmful mutations by positive selection, but it looks like a derived mutation away from the MRCA with the bat-CoV. So we can see the effect of not using the MRCA of the epidemic as the root, in a study where we are looking for selection in the epidemic (not the wrong root, but the wrong root for this particular analysis)―the effect is that the faux &amp;ldquo;derived&amp;rdquo; substitutions make it look like we have an excess of high-frequency synonymous substitutions when we don&#39;t, and to a potentially false conclusion of purifying selection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors also identified &amp;ldquo;derived&amp;rdquo; variants that they presented as favouring transmission or virulence, but this was not convincing to many researchers. You can read more about these problems in &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/ve/veaa034&#34;&gt;MacLean et al 2020&lt;/a&gt; and for a general warning of the pitfalls relating to inferring selection and new virulent strains of SARS-CoV-2, this is a good read &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41564-020-0738-5&#34;&gt;Villabona-Arenas, Hanage &amp;amp; Tully, 2020&lt;/a&gt;. I think the general rule is, try not to get lost in your own analysis. Imagine you are someone else, a critical reviewer, and ask, what else could explain what I am seeing, aside from what I want to be true?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Publish what you see, not what you think is there!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top image: &amp;ldquo;The logo of the ARTIC network&amp;rdquo; Credit: &lt;a href=&#34;https://artic.network/&#34;&gt;ARTIC Network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A virus goes missing―genomics explains reappearance of lost virus</title>
      <link>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/blog/frozenevol/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 10:48:46 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/blog/frozenevol/</guid>
      <description>












&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://InfrPopGen.github.io/img/BTVphylo.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://InfrPopGen.github.io/img/BTVphylo.png&#34; alt=&#34;phylogeny for BTV8&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;400&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This investigation into the re-emergence of Bluetongue virus serotype 8 (BTV-8)&lt;/strong&gt; in France 2015 is a fine example of phylogenetic epidemiology in action. In the 2006 outbreak BTV spread to affect 16 countries and killed many livestock animals, particularly sheep, with losses to European agriculture in the billions of Euros. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluetongue_disease&#34;&gt;BTV is an arthropod-borne virus&lt;/a&gt; of ruminants and was considered successfully controlled through vaccination by early 2010, but is now enzootic to France. Consequently, David Pascall, Kyriaki Nomikou, and colleagues in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gla.ac.uk/researchinstitutes/iii/cvr/staff/groups/palmarinigroup/&#34;&gt;Glasgow&lt;/a&gt; and across Europe, sought to explain the unexpected outbreak in France by applying phylogenetics to a data-set of 164 complete BTV-8 genomes sampled throughout the first (2006-2009) and second (2015) outbreaks. Cessation of vaccination in 2010 was followed by a steady decline in seropositivity in cattle until 2014; thus a reintroduction (rather than cryptic sub-clinical transmission) appeared likely. To avoid culture effects most samples were taken directly from infected cattle. The phylogeny showed genomes of the second outbreak to be monophyletic (all in one clade or lineage, with no other genomes mixed in) and entirely nested within those of the first. Notably, the branch linking the two outbreaks was suspiciously short given the substitution rate of BTV-8 and the five years between the outbreaks. The ancestral sequence was reconstructed for the second outbreak and found to differ at only 4 sites from its closest relative in the first epidemic, whereas samples collected in 2006 differed from those in 2008 by up to 56 sites. Indeed root-to-tip regression (of tree branch lengths against sampling times), applied to a tree that included the reconstructed ancestor of the second outbreak, dated the ancestor as having been circulating in late March 2008. The authors were able to effectively rule out dormancy in some life-stage of the arthropod vector, and latency in some accessory host, because five years was just too long. Noting that BTV has been detected in the semen of viraemic bulls and rams, the authors proposed that the 2015 outbreak may have arisen from use of frozen semen, embryos or colostrum, which is a common practice in livestock farming. The study has been published in PLoS Biology and is available open-access directly from the publisher &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3000673&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top image: &amp;ldquo;Timescaled phylogenetic tree of BTV-8 samples collected during the European outbreaks between 2006 and 2018&amp;rdquo; by Pascall DJ, Nomikou K, Bréard E, Zientara S, Filipe AdS, Hoffmann B, et al. &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3000673&#34;&gt;2020&lt;/a&gt;, used under &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
