<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>virology | Phylodynamics</title>
    <link>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/tags/virology/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://InfrPopGen.github.io/tags/virology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>virology</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© S.W. Attwood, 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 10:48:46 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/img/ez01.jpg</url>
      <title>virology</title>
      <link>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/tags/virology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>A virus goes missing―genomics explains reappearance of lost virus</title>
      <link>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/blog/frozenevol/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 10:48:46 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/blog/frozenevol/</guid>
      <description>












&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://InfrPopGen.github.io/img/BTVphylo.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://InfrPopGen.github.io/img/BTVphylo.png&#34; alt=&#34;phylogeny for BTV8&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;400&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This investigation into the re-emergence of Bluetongue virus serotype 8 (BTV-8)&lt;/strong&gt; in France 2015 is a fine example of phylogenetic epidemiology in action. In the 2006 outbreak BTV spread to affect 16 countries and killed many livestock animals, particularly sheep, with losses to European agriculture in the billions of Euros. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluetongue_disease&#34;&gt;BTV is an arthropod-borne virus&lt;/a&gt; of ruminants and was considered successfully controlled through vaccination by early 2010, but is now enzootic to France. Consequently, David Pascall, Kyriaki Nomikou and colleagues in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gla.ac.uk/researchinstitutes/iii/cvr/staff/groups/palmarinigroup/&#34;&gt;Glasgow&lt;/a&gt; and across Europe, sought to explain the unexpected outbreak in France by applying phylogenetics to a data-set of 164 complete BTV-8 genomes sampled throughout the first (2006-2009) and second (2015) outbreaks. Cessation of vaccination in 2010 was followed by a steady decline in seropositivity in cattle until 2014; thus a reintroduction (rather than cryptic sub-clinical transmission) appeared likely. To avoid culture effects most samples were taken directly from infected cattle. The phylogeny showed genomes of the second outbreak to be monophyletic (all in one clade or lineage, with no other genomes mixed in) and entirely nested within those of the first. Notably, the branch linking the two outbreaks was suspiciously short given the substitution rate of BTV-8 and the five years between the outbreaks. The ancestral sequence was reconstructed for the second outbreak and found to differ at only 4 sites from its closest relative in the first epidemic, whereas samples collected in 2006 differed from those in 2008 by up to 56 sites. Indeed root-to-tip regression (of tree branch lengths against sampling times) applied to a tree that included the reconstructed ancestor of the second outbreak, dated the ancestor as having been circulating in late March 2008. The authors were able to effectively rule out dormancy in some life-stage of the arthropod vector, and latency in some accessory host, because five years was just too long. Noting that BTV has been detected in the semen of viraemic bulls and rams, the authors proposed that the 2015 outbreak may have arisen from use of frozen semen, embryos or colostrum, which is a common practice in livestock farming. The study has been published in PLoS Biology and is available open-access directly from the publisher &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3000673&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top image: &amp;ldquo;Timescaled phylogenetic tree of BTV-8 samples collected during the European outbreaks between 2006 and 2018&amp;rdquo; by Pascall DJ, Nomikou K, Bréard E, Zientara S, Filipe AdS, Hoffmann B, et al. &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3000673&#34;&gt;2020&lt;/a&gt;, used under &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
