<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>immunology | Phylodynamics</title>
    <link>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/categories/immunology/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://InfrPopGen.github.io/categories/immunology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>immunology</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© S.W. Attwood, 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 15:15:04 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/img/ez01.jpg</url>
      <title>immunology</title>
      <link>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/categories/immunology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of the human―virus interaction in COVID-19</title>
      <link>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/blog/sars_evol_immunity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 15:15:04 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://InfrPopGen.github.io/blog/sars_evol_immunity/</guid>
      <description>












&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://InfrPopGen.github.io/img/clonotypes.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://InfrPopGen.github.io/img/clonotypes.png&#34; alt=&#34;heatmap&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt; If there is unfamiliar terminology here, then it may help to read these posts in order, starting with &amp;ldquo;Is SARS-CoV-2 evolving?&amp;rdquo; of 18th May 2020. Definitions of terms are in bold to help in finding them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phylogenetics can give clues about how SARS-CoV-2 battles the anti-viral responses of its hosts&lt;/strong&gt;―two recent papers considered the C-&amp;gt;U hypermutation which, like other coronaviruses, is a feature of the SARS-CoV-2 genome. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.05.01.072330&#34;&gt;Peter Simmonds&amp;rsquo; preprint&lt;/a&gt; focused on treating the low &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CpG_site&#34;&gt;CpG content&lt;/a&gt; of the CoV genomes as a phylogenetic character that tells us something about events in their history, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.abb5813&#34;&gt;the paper by Salvatore Giorgio et al (2020)&lt;/a&gt; gives further examination of the anti-viral aspects. Simmonds noted that there are about four times the number of C-&amp;gt;U transitions in the SARS-CoV-2 genome than expected by chance, which is high even among RNA viruses, and that around half of non-synonymous mutations are C-&amp;gt;U substitutions―suggesting they might be important in the evolution of the virus (but see below). This excess increases 10-fold if the C-&amp;gt;U is flanked by a certain &lt;strong&gt;motif&lt;/strong&gt; (i.e. specific sequence pattern), which Simmonds noted are favoured by certain &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4930407/&#34;&gt;APOBEC&lt;/a&gt; proteins. Some APOBECs are thought able to introduce mutations to RNA viral genomes by deamination of cytidines, with the mutations introduced as an anti-viral defence. The fact that these viruses show low GC content, but the G+A content is relatively normal, would fit with an APOBEC acting on the genomic (positive) strand of the virus, exposed in the cytoplasm, before replication complex formation―otherwise both strands would be present, and susceptible to mutation as the genome is replicated―the GA content would then fall with the GC. The same idea (lack of symmetry) argues against the mutations being errors of the &lt;strong&gt;viral RdRp&lt;/strong&gt; (RNA-dependent RNA-polymerase, the enzyme that the viruses uses to copy its own genome). APOBEC RNA-editing would also explain the strangely high dN/dS ratio in SARS-CoV-2 because it would not be shaped by natural selection. Indeed, we would have APOBEC introducing variants and natural selection removing any that were deleterious. Of course, we can imagine that these viruses would evolve to avoid using sequences that APOBECs target; however, there is a diverse family of APOBECs and they vary among host species. Simmonds observed that the hypermutation is greatest in close relatives of SARS-CoV-2 and reduces as more divergent lineages are considered; this could be because the human SARS-CoVs have only recently begun to infect humans, whereas the seasonal CoVs that have long circulated in humans have adapted to our APOBECs and restored their GC content. The implication is that SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 are still adapted to bat APOBECs (or to whatever the ancestral hosts were). Giorgio et al. take the story a little further, and look at another deanimase family, the ADARs, as well as APOBEC; they found frequently overrepresented stop codons in transcribed viral RNAs rather than genomic, which supported an anti-viral role for these enzymes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we tend to learn most from papers that attract criticism, I should mention the &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msaa094&#34;&gt;paper in MBE by Xia (2020)&lt;/a&gt; here. Xia came up with a nice idea (those are often the ones that draw flak), as he found CpG levels in some canine alphacoronaviruses as low as in SARS-CoV-2, the record holder for low CpG among these CoVs (although human seasonal cold virus CoV HKU1 might be lower). He reasoned that the ancestor of SARS-CoV-2 may have been subjected to a canine immune environment, and on that basis argued that SARS-CoV-2 jumped from bats to some canine and then to humans. In a recent (aren&#39;t they all?) preprint &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.05.08.083816v1&#34;&gt;Digard et al (2020)&lt;/a&gt; aligned nearly 200 genomes of SARS-CoVs and various coronaviruses transmitting in animals. They found that although CpG levels were lowest in human and canine coronaviruses and highest in bat and rodent, there was much range overlap, which makes Xia&#39;s nice idea more shaky. These authors all noted that the low CpG may well be to avoid the action of Zinc-finger Antiviral Protein (ZAP), which binds to viral RNAs at their CpG motifs (an addition to the APOBEC explanation). Interestingly, Digard&#39;s group found almost normal CpG levels at two loci, &lt;em&gt;E ORF&lt;/em&gt; and the coding region of &lt;em&gt;ORF10&lt;/em&gt; (an ORF is an &lt;strong&gt;Open Reading Frame&lt;/strong&gt;, the coding part of a gene that can be translated, but viruses can have overlapping ORFs, or &amp;ldquo;sub-ORFs&amp;rdquo; if you like, that&#39;s not an official term!). These two loci also showed much less CpG suppression than the rest of their genomes in bat- and pangolin-CoVs sampled nearly a decade ago. The implication is that selection had not removed this pattern over the years, and so it is a derived trait that was selected for before SARS-CoVs began to transmit widely among humans. In support of this, a phylogenetic tree estimated with only &lt;em&gt;E ORF&lt;/em&gt; sequences for the 7 human-CoVs and 96 bat-CoVs showed the human-CoVs scattered among the bat-CoV lineages and with CpG levels matching their closest bat-CoV relatives. They suggest that the high CpG in &lt;em&gt;E ORF&lt;/em&gt; might be because it is transcribed late in the infection process, when attack by ZAP is less of a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;E ORF&lt;/em&gt; story is a good example of how phylogenetics can help us understand the anti-viral reponses during infection, and the strategies SARS-CoV-2 has been using to avoid them as it evolved and moved from host to host. Now let&#39;s look at some sequencing studies on the immune response itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;APOBECS are part of the interferon-induced innate immune response (they have links with adaptive response too, but that is another topic), but &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.05.20.106294v1&#34;&gt;Galson et al (2020)&lt;/a&gt; use sequencing data, and a nearest-neighbour kind of clustering algorithm, to directly explore the humoral immune response to SARS-CoV-2. They compared the IGHA and IGHG B-Cell Receptor (BCR) sequences for 19 patients with those for healthy individuals. The numbers of mutations showed a bimodal frequency plot (i.e. two humps), which suggests an expanding population―i.e. a population of B-cells that had only just &amp;ldquo;switched&amp;rdquo; on to the presence of the virus. Nevertheless, the larger clonal expansions revealed by the sequence network showed many mutations, which fits with their having activated from memory of a previously encountered antigen. Convergent BCR sequences were also seen, with very similar sequences among different patients, and even between UK and US studies; this convergence is good news for vaccine development, as it implies that a vaccine that works across diverse lineages of virus is feasible. We also saw signs of activation from memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To counter that possibly good news, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.05.21.109272v1&#34;&gt;Cheng et al. (2020)&amp;lsquo;s preprint&lt;/a&gt; is potentially worrying, but models are never perfect so&amp;hellip;. These authors modelled the shape (and charge) of the &amp;ldquo;spike&amp;rdquo; protein, which is what the virus uses to recognise ACE2 receptors on our cells and trigger the process of cell entry. The models indicated a 20 amino acid motif in spike that mimics a superantigen called staphylococcal entero-toxin B (SEB), which is known to be the trigger for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.qedbio.com/blog/superantigens-elicit-cytokine-storm-responsible-t-cells-identified/&#34;&gt;toxic shock or the cytokine storm&lt;/a&gt; in humans. In SARS-CoV-2 the motif appears to be palindromic so, when the reverse direction is also included, this doubles the stretch of sequence to match with the superantigen peptide. The superantigen motif is not found in any other SARS coronavirus, such as SARS-CoV from the 2002-2004 outbreak. Probably most controversially the models indicate that some &lt;strong&gt;Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms&lt;/strong&gt; (SNPs, or substitutions at a single site that persist in a population at non-negligible frequencies) currently circulating in Europe and the US may increase the superantigenicity of the SEB-like motif. Among these is the infamous D641G, which I have to write about next, which may interact with MHCII to strengthen the association with T-cell receptors involved in cytokine storm initiation. The authors suggest that this may explain the higher rates of cytokine storm in Europe and US and the appearance in Europe of SARS-CoV-2 related inflammatory syndrome in children. It is important to note that without a heap of empirical evidence to back these suggestions, the indications of computer models are just that, indications only. After all, there are many possible explanations for many things!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS Just for fun, you may want to think about what the implications are of C-&amp;gt;G hypermutation, especially by APOBECs, on phylogenetics (i.e. on estimating evolutionary trees). How might that affect our SARS-CoV-2 evolutionary trees?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top image: &amp;ldquo;Heatmap of the 777 convergent COVID-19-associated clonotypes (observed between 4 or more COVID-19 participants)&amp;rdquo; by Galson, J. D.; Schaetzle, S.; Bashford-Rogers, R. J. M.; Raybould, M. I. J.; Kovaltsuk, A.; Kilpatrick, G. J.; Minter, R.; Finch, D. K.; Dias, J.; James, L.; Thomas, G., et al. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.05.20.106294v1&#34;&gt;2020&lt;/a&gt;, used under &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
